Guide to the Woodman Taylor collection AD.MC.079
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Woodman Taylor collection
2011-2019
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Taylor, Woodman
AD.MC.079
1.67 Linear Feet in 4 archival file boxes.
Printed material related to art exhibitions, art organizations, and related activities, in the United Arab Emirates, collected by educator and art historian Woodman Taylor. Includes exhibition catalogs, exhibition guides and maps, brochures, and issues of serial publications.
Conditions governing access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Gift of Woodman Taylor, 2019-2020.
Arrangement
In most series, the arrangement is chronological by date of art exhibition.
Biographical note
Woodman Taylor is an art historian and curator who specializes in South Asian and Islamic art. He lived in the United Arab Emirates from 2012-2020, and during that time served on the faculty of the American University of Dubai from 2012 to 2018, as a professor of art history, as well as chairing the Department of Visual Communication. From 2018-2020, he served as a consultant on several projects, including at Zayed University and New York University Abu Dhabi.
While in the UAE, he took an active interest in the local art scene, and developed an expertise and interest in photography that led him to co-found the journal "Tribe: Photography and New Media from the Arab World," published in Dubai.
Prior to his work in the UAE, Taylor served on the faculty of the University of Illinois at Chicago as an assistant professor of art history (1996-2006), as assistant curator for South Asian and Islamic art at the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston (2006-2008), and director of development for the South-East Asia Center in Chicago (2008-2012), among other positions.
Taylor earned a bachelors degree in Asian history and ethnomusicology from Wesleyan College, a masters in information science from Simmons College in Boston, and a masters and doctorate in art history from the University of Chicago.
Content Description
The Woodman Taylor collection consists of printed material related to art exhibitions, art organizations, and related activities, in the United Arab Emirates, collected by educator and art historian Woodman Taylor. The collection includes exhibition catalogs, exhibition guides and maps, brochures, and issues of serial publications.
Most of the material in this collection was acquired by Taylor while he lived and worked in the United Arab Emirates from 2012-2020. While not meant to be a comprhensive collection, it nevertheless provides a glimpse of the vibrant arts scene during that time, as experienced by Taylor through exhibitions at museums and galleries, and other arts-related events that he attended.
Representation is particularly strong for exhibitions hosted by the Sharjah Arts Foundation, but also includes materials from other arts organizations based in Sharjah, such as the Maraya Art Centre and Barjeel Foundation. Also represented are several galleries from Dubai's Alserkal Avenue, along with other events and venues in Dubai. In addition, a few venues in Abu Dhabi are included as well, including the NYU Abu Dhabi Art Gallery and Zayed University.
Most of the exhibition catalogs, booklets, and maps are bilingual, printed in both Arabic and English.
Separated materials
Several exhibition catalogs and other publications have been cataloged separately, and are searchable in the library catalog of New York University Abu Dhabi.
Art, Modern -- United Arab Emirates -- 21st century -- Exhibitions; Taylor, Woodman; Sharjah Art Foundation
- NYU Abu Dhabi Art Gallery, 2014-2019
  - Diana al-Hadid: Phantom Limb. [exhibition booklet], Undated, circa 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Slavs and Tartars: Mirrors for Princes, Both Sides of the Tongue [exhibition booklet], February 28-May 30, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Permanent Temporariness. Sandi Hilal and Alessandro Petti, curated by Salwa Mikdadi and Bana Kattan. [Exhibition booklet], February 24-June 9, 2018 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Attar, Ammar al. Cinemas in the UAE. Project Space, NYU Abu Dhabi [brochure], 21 October - 5 November 2018 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speculative Landscapes: Areej Kaoud, Ayman Zedani, Jumairy, Raja'a Khalid [exhibition booklet], September 16-December 7, 2019 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Sharjah Art Foundation, 2012-2020
  - General, 2015-2019
    - The Flying Saucer. [series of postcards of photos of structure], undated, circa 2015 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Leuli Eshraghi. Tagatanu'u. [exhibition text], 2017 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - March Project 2018 [exhibition guide, multiple artists], 29 September 2018 - 10 January 2019 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Sharjah Film Platform, 18-26 Jan 2019: Film screenings, talks, workshops [event program], 18 - 26 January 2019 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sharjah Biennial 14: Leaving the Echo Chamber [exhibition map], 7 March - 10 June 2019 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - March Meeting. Leaving the Echo Chamber [guide to events and artists], 9-11 March 2019 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Sharjapan: The Poetics of Space. Al Hamriyah Studios, Sharjah [postcard], 21 November 2018 - 15 January 2019 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition guides, small format booklets, 2012-2020
    - Lara Favaretto. Just Knocked Out (Beit al Serkal, Sharjah), 15 Dec 2012 - 6 Feb 2013 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ahmed Mater. 100 Found Objects (SAF Art Spaces, Sharjah), 22 Feb - 22 May 2014 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Rasheed Araeen. Before and After Minimalism. Curated by Hoor al Qasimi (SAF Art Spaces), 13 March - 13 June 2014 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Do it [bil 'arabee] (Bait al Shamsi, Sharjah), 23 Jan - 23 April 2016 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Kamal Youssef: Egyptian Surrealism's Time Capsule. Curated by Hoor al Qasimi and Salah Hassan (Sharjah Art Museum), 17 September - 17 November 2016 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Robert Breer. Time Flies. Curated by Hoor Al Qasimi (The Flying Saucer, Sharjah), 1 October 2016 - 9 January 2017 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Ahmed Morsi. A Dialogic Imagination (Sharjah Art Museum), 1 March - 3 June 2017 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Latif Al Ani. Through the Lens, 1953-1979 (Gallery 4, Al Mureijah Square, Sharjah), 16 March - 16 June 2018 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - March Meeting: Active Forms. Curated by Reem Shadid (Dar al Nadwa, Calligraphy Square, Sharjah), 17-19 March 2018 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ala Younis. Steps Toward the Impossible (Gallery 6, Al Mureijah Square), 29 September 2018 - 5 January 2019 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Frank Bowling. Mappa Mundi (Gallery 6, Al Mureijah Square), 29 September 2018 - 5 January 2019 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Amal Kenawy. Frozen Memory (Bait al Serkal, Arts Square, Sharjah), 3 November 2018 - 19 January 2019 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Vantage Point Sharjah 2019 (Gallery ½, Al Mureijah Square, Sharjah), 6 July - 6 October 2019 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Adam Henein. Lasting Impressions (Sharjah Art Museum), 21 September - 16 November 2019 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Air Arabia Curator in Residence--'32: The Rescore (Gallery 6, Al Mureijah Square, Sharjah), 27 September 2019 - 5 January 2020 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Akram Zaatari. Against Photography (Gallery 3/4, Al Mureijah Square, Sharjah), 27 September 2019 - 10 January 2020 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - March Project 2019. (Bait Obaid al Shamsi, Calligraphy Square and Bait al Hurma in Al Mureijah Square, Sharjah), 12 October 2019 - 20 January 2020 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Zayed University, 2014-2017
  - Showcase: Senior Exhibition 2017. College of Arts and Creative Enterprises (CACE), Zayed University. Exhibition Catalog. [exhibition at Manarat al Saadiyat, Abu Dhabi, 25 April - 7 May 2017, and d3 Dubai Design District, 9-12 May 2017 ](Zayed University, 2017). [book: open shelves]
  - ISEA 2014. Location: The 20th International Symposium on Electronic Art. (Catalog), 30 October - 8 November 2014 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Various: Abu Dhabi, 2017-2019
  - Community and Critique: Salama bint Hamdan Emerging Artists Fellowship, Cohort 5. Warehouse 421, Abu Dhabi. (with post cards and brochures from Warehouse 421)., 2017-2018 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Warehouse 421. Assorted postcards, 2017-2018 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Zayed: The Soft Power. [Exhibition Guide] ADMAF Pavilion at Abu Dhabi Art 2018, Manarat al Saadiyat, 14 -17 November 2018 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Structures of Meaning, Architectures of Perception: Abu Dhabi Art 2018 Gateway. Curated by Hammad Nasar and Sophie Persson. Manarat al Saadiyat. Exhibition Booklet, 14 November 2018 - 26 January 2019 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters. Abu Dhabi. [n.l.]., 14 November 2018 - 26 January 2019 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Abdul Qader Al Rais: 50 Years of Art. Manarat al Saadiyat [exhibition guide, Arabic and English], 20 December 2018 - 23 March 2019 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Culture Summit 2019. Abu Dhabi. [program] (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Various: Dubai, 2011-2019
  - The Farjam Collection: Islamic Art Exhibition, Undated, circa 2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Edge of Arabia Dubai presents: terminal, exhibition passport; DIFC, Dubai, March-April 2011 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - This momentary (Al Khor series). Reem Falakanaz [booklet, published under Sikka Art Fair], 2013 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sikka [event program, Dubai Art Season], 15 - 25 March 2014 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Kazem, Mohammed. Sound of Objects, Gallery Isabel van den Eynde, Dubai, 3 November 2014 - 4 January 2015 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - UFO Hunters, by Mehreen Murtaza. [Booklet commissioned to accompany the art project Deep Earth Object, 2015. Installation at Alserkal Avenue, Dubai], 16 March - 16 May 2015 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Jean-Paul Najar Foundation (Alserkal Avenue): various brochures, 2016 and undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Is Old Gold? Curated by Cristiana de Marchi and Muhanad Ali. The Gallery of Light, Dubai Community Theatre and Arts Centre [exhibition guide], February 21 - April 7, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Artmap. No. 27. (Dubai: Dubai Culture?), February - August 2018 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Field Meeting Take 6: Thinking Collections. Curated by Leeza Ahmady. Asia Contemporary Art Week / Alserkal Avenue, Dubai. [Event program], January 25 - 26, 2019 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Get Closer: GPP Photoweek 2019 [event program], February 4 - 9, 2019 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Mohamed Ahmed Ibrahim: The Space Between the Eyelid and the Eyeball. [gallery brochure]. Lawrie Shabibi, Alserkal Avenue, Dubai., 5 March - 9 May 2019 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "School is a Factory?" Global Art Forum. Art Dubai, Madinat Jumeirah, March 20-21, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Exit from the Entrance. Shreyas Karie. [exhibition guide], May 15 - July 31, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Altered Inheritances: Home is a Foreign Place. Shilka Gupta and Zarina. [exhibition guide], March 18 - July 13, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fazal Rizvi. This is a Mirage, an Image, a Monument, or a Shrine. [exhibition guide]., September 2019 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Body Building. Curated by Nada Raza. Ishara Art Foundation / Alserkal Avenue., September 12 - December 14, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Various: Sharjah, 2014-2019, and undated
  - The Present: Contemporary Art from the Emirates. Curated by Noor Al Suwaidi. Maraya Art Centre, Sharjah [exhibition catalog], undated, circa 2012 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Wafaa Bilal. The Hierarchy of Being. Curated by Sara Raza. Sharjah: Maraya Art Centre, undated, circa 2013 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Islamopolitan. Maraya Art Centre, Sharjah, undated, circa 2014 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Modes and Methods: an exhibition of UAE artists. Barjeel Art Foundation / Google House, Sharjah. [Exhibition guide], May 6 - 7, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lasting Impressions: Noor Ali Rashid. Sharjah Art Museum. [exhibition brochure], October 22 - December 6, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Ministry of Graphic Design. Fikra Design Biennial 01. Sharjah. [exhibition brochure/map], November 9 - 30, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Africa Institute Newsletter, Issue No. 1. [guide to events], Autumn 2018 - Spring 2019 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Some of those Mysteries." Nujoom Al Ghanem. Islamic Arts Festival, 21st Edition, Sharjah., Undated, 2018-2019 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Various: venues outside of the United Arab Emirates, 2012-2019
  - Atul Bhalla. What Will Be My Defeat? (Hamburg: Free River Zone Hamburg), 2012 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Binary States: an exhibition celebrating overlapping elements in Emirati-Indian cultures, Kochi-Muziris Biennale (Kochi, Kerala, India), 2016 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Thought is also a Matter. Curator: Raju Sutar. Kochi-Muziris Biennale [exhibition guide]. Kochi, Kerala, India., 2018 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Tribe: Contemporary Photography from the Arab World. Curators: Janet Bellotto and Dr. Woodman Taylor. American University Museum, Washington, DC [exhibition brochures], 2018 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - American University Beirut. The Permanent Collection. [exhibition guide], undated, circa 2018 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Cut/Gash/Slash. Adachi Masao: A Militant Theory of Landscape. Curated by Octavian Esanu and Go Hirakawa. American University of Beirut [exhibition guide], March 2019 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Various: serial publications, 2012-2018
  - The State: Vol. 1: Voicings / articulations / utterances. The State, Dubai., Spring 2012 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Di'van: a Journal of Accounts. No. 5. (Sydney: Divan Art Journal and University of NSW). ISSN 2207-1563, December 2018 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Gagoue, Louis Philippe de. The Ivory Coast. Brownbook (insert), undated (Box 4, Folder 23)